This video is sponsored by Brilliant. Go
to brilliant.org/theplainbagel.
Scan the QR code on screen or click the
link in the description to start
learning for free today and for 20% off
an annual premium subscription. Hey
everyone, it's Richard. You're watching
the plain bagel. The idea of countries
targeting a given inflation rate is
something that most of us take for
granted when discussing central bank
policies. After all, many countries,
including here in Canada and the United
States, task their central banks with
maintaining price stability. So it makes
sense that they establish some sort of
public goal for guiding their monetary
policy and tracking their progress. And
today we have roughly 45 individual
countries and the entire Euro area
establishing some sort of public
inflation target with many including all
of the G7 nations, the Euro zone, and
even just recently China opting for a 2%
target, meaning that every year they
look to have their price levels increase
by 2%.
But why? After all, it's obvious that a
2% inflation rate would be better than
say 100%. It might still sound a bit
arbitrary or even backwards. If the
central bank's objective is to maintain
price stability,
why not target 0% inflation? Or heck,
why not try to lower prices so that
households can actually afford more
goods over time with their savings put
aside? Well, the truth is that the
origin of this 2% target is in fact
pretty arbitrary and probably a lot more
recent than you might otherwise expect.
In fact, the first country to implement
an inflation target, New Zealand, only
did so 36 years ago. And the US Federal
Reserve, didn't have an explicit
inflation target until 1996.
And even then, the target was only made
public starting in 2012. And yet,
despite all this, it's quickly become
part of central bank dogma with Japan up
until recently even pushing to get its
inflation rate up to 2% after years of
stagnant and falling prices. So, what's
so special about this 2% rate? Well,
today we'll talk about the bizarre
origin of this figure, why it's been
maintained, and the justifications for
targeting any inflation at all, the
arguments against such a target, and how
these policies ultimately impact the
economy as a whole. But to start things
off, let's start again with that origin
of this figure back in New Zealand. You
see, in 1989, as the world was still
grappling with fairly high inflation
rates, we saw the country who itself was
dealing with years of double-digit
inflation pass a bill that sought to
make its central bank independent from
the government to allow to freely pursue
monetary policy. And while not the focus
of the legislation, the bill also
instructed the finance minister and the
head of the central bank to establish an
inflation target with the country
ultimately settling on a target range of
0 to 2% inflation every year. And as for
how we arrived to this figure that would
forever shape monetary policy moving
forward, well, seemingly a TV interview.
You see, a year earlier, the previous
finance minister, Roger Douglas, in an
interview highlighted that he would like
to target inflation of between zero and
1% uh before this legislation had been
passed. And allegedly, the country just
kind of went with that with the central
bank and the finance minister increasing
the upper bound to 2% to allow for a bit
more flexibility.
That's it. This monumentally important
figure was effectively pulled out of
thin air. So, yeah, not much of a robust
or empirical process for getting to this
figure. But what's interesting about
this policy is that it seemingly worked.
Inflation dropped from its double-digit
range in the late 1980s to within its
target range after just a few years with
economists finding that by communicating
an inflation rate to the economy, it
actually helped central banks achieve
this objective by influencing expected
inflation. You see, if a central bank is
viewed as credible and independent by
market participants, then communicating
an inflation target helps to anchor
inflation expectations, which influences
the behavior of those market
participants. Banks will assume a 2%
interest rate when they make their
loans. Unions will bargain for a 2%
annual increase to ensure that salaries
keep up with that expected inflation
rate. And these actions in and of
themselves lead inflation to becoming
that 2%. So despite the experimental
nature of this regime, it quickly gained
traction among many developed nations.
And despite there being not much of an
empirical process behind it, there were
still some key arguments supporting the
idea of targeting a low positive
inflation rate that are still used to
the state to justify the figure.
Firstly, 2% is viewed as being low
enough as to not materially impact the
purchasing power of the dollar from year
to year. Yes, of course, any money that
you stow under your mattress for the
long term is going to see its purchasing
power fall quite a bit over your
lifetime. Even at a 2% inflation rate, a
dollar today loses half of its value
over 35 years. But in the short term,
it's viewed as having a minimal impact
on the dollar store value. Secondly,
having an inflation target above 0%
gives central banks more room to carry
out monetary policy. Uh you see,
inflation rates have a direct impact on
interest rates charged in an economy. uh
because naturally if the money you lend
out to people is losing value over time,
you're going to want to be compensated
for that lost value when that amount
when that loan is eventually paid back
to you. So lenders will directly
increase the interest rates they charge
based on expected inflation rates. So
the higher the central bank's targeted
inflation rate, the higher interest
rates in the economy should be. And
having higher interest rates give
central banks more room to cut set
interest rates to stimulate the economy
given that 0% sort of stands as a lower
bound. Yes, we've seen examples of
negative interest rates, but for the
most part, 0% is the least you can
charge on lent money. So, by targeting a
higher inflation rate, central banks can
have a larger impact on the economy if
they expect a recession or severe
contraction. And another aspect as well
with all of this is that a positive
inflation rate makes it easier for
companies to reduce real wages of their
employees in response to economic
shocks. Now, I know what you're
thinking. Richard, what the hell? Why
are we making it easier for companies to
cut our incomes? That uh sounds like a
conspiracy to screw over workers. And
we'll get into the shortcomings of this
philosophy in a moment. But the point is
that when an economy sees demand fall
during a recession, for economies to
stabilize themselves, companies
theoretically should be able to reduce
wages, lay off employees, and ultimately
lower their prices to allow the economy
to return to its full GDP potential. The
problem is that in practice, wage cuts
are actually pretty rare with companies
instead opting to just laying off
employees when they need to reduce their
labor costs. But with a positive
inflation rate, companies can keep wages
stagnant, thereby effectively cutting
the wages in real terms and allowing
economic activity to normalize and reach
that point of equilibrium with the same
principle applying to interest rates,
which can dip into negative territory in
real terms when there's positive
inflation. And finally, the last
justification for why central banks
target a 2% inflation rate is that it's
viewed as being high enough to avoid
deflation or price levels decreasing
over time. Uh since inflation often
deviates from the central bank's target
in any given year, the higher the
target, the less likely it is for price
levels to dip into deflation territory.
Now, that does bring us to a question
that many find quite frustrating. Why do
economists treat deflation like the
boogeyman? After all, it sounds like a
good deal. Who wouldn't want prices to
fall every year to reward them for
putting money aside? All this just kind
of sounds like an excuse for the
government to inflate their currency.
Well, there is certainly that
consideration. And Milton Friedman, a
famous economist, once called inflation
taxes without legislation, which is a
pretty fair assessment. Inflation is
fueled by government spending at the
expense of household wealth. But the
general concern is that while yes,
deflation could be beneficial for the
households that have meaningful savings
put aside, it does come with a number of
other consequences. uh the main one
being that deflation is thought to
reduce economic activity by just doing
that incentivizing individuals to save
their money rather than spending it.
After all, if the car or dishwasher that
you want to buy is going to be cheaper a
year from now or even 2 or 3 years down
the line, then it's going to incentivize
people to put off that purchase until
it's absolutely needed. Compared to
inflation, which incentivizes people to
spend their money now and boost economic
activity, economists also fears
something called deflationary spiral. As
prices fall, companies are faced with
lower profits, which leads them to cut
costs by cutting jobs and lowering
wages, which leads to less spending and
investing in the economy, which brings
us back to more deflation and continues
the vicious cycle. Something that can
ultimately end in a severe economic
contraction that can prove difficult to
pull out of with monetary policy given
again the lower bound on interest rates.
something we've seen in countries like
Japan, which experienced the so-called
lost decade in the 1990s, where crash in
its stock and real estate market was
followed by a decade of sluggish
performance and low inflation or even
deflation. And when we're sort of
assessing the pros and cons to the
economy as a whole rather than
individuals, you might have caught one
of the important implications for
households is that falling real income
as well as rising unemployment. So yes,
savings might become more valuable, but
it might get harder to accumulate any
money in the first place. So, while
deflation can be great for those who
already have money, it can make it
harder to accumulate and can even
increase the real burden of outstanding
debts. Because things like mortgage and
credit card balances have a fixed dollar
amount that you owe at the end of the
term, that amount is going to become
more and more valuable in real terms,
making it harder and harder to pay off,
especially if you face falling income,
which is important when you consider how
indebted many countries and their
households are in the current economic
environment. Now, of course, there's the
argument that inflation has incentivized
this debt accumulation over time. And
it's worth highlighting that not all
deflation is necessarily bad.
Technological innovation, for example,
frequently leads to productivity gains
and falling prices. And while deflation
can be a sign or trigger of falling
demand, we have seen periods of strong
economic growth coupled with falling
price levels due to increases in supply.
Again, possibly coming from
technological innovations. One research
paper by the National Bureau of Economic
Research, for example, highlights that
during the late 1800s, the global
economy saw both falling prices and
rapid economic expansion in the face of
the industrial revolution. With the
paper arguing that while the constrained
money supply from the gold standard
negatively impacted economic activity,
this was more than offset by the
positive impact of those technological
advancements. And one of the biggest
issues people have with positive
inflation targeting is that while
theoretically it shouldn't really matter
what this target is, given that you
should see incomes increase at the same
pace as inflation and savings rates at
bank accounts compensate for this lost
spending power. In practice, inflation
does not apply to all these areas
evenly. And you can see wages, for
example, fall behind despite price
levels continuing to increase. Even
measuring inflation and tracking the
progress of this 2% target has proven a
contentious thing. While central banks
often use the consumer price index or
some variant like the core consumer
price index to assess how closely they
are to their target, these indices don't
always capture the actual price
increases that households are
experiencing given that they don't
account for things like substitution
where households change their spending
behavior based on changing prices. So,
it's worth noting that not everyone
agrees with a 2% target. And there are
known costs to inflation. Beyond the
deterioration of savings, inflation also
comes with menu costs, meaning the costs
associated with companies having to
frequently change the price of their
goods. And inflation tends to impose a
higher tax burden on households given
that tax brackets aren't often indexed
to inflation. So, a higher nominal
household income leads to a higher
percentage tax rate even if real wages
aren't increasing. However, the problem
is that it's difficult to prove
empirically which targeting regime,
whether it be moderate inflation or even
deflation, would be optimal for economic
activity given that most persistently
deflationary economies existed before
the Second World War when data
collection wasn't to the same degree or
quality. In fact, one of the biggest
criticisms of schools of economic
thought that advocate for deflation is
that they don't have much empirical
evidence to support their arguments.
It's also difficult, of course, to
isolate the influence of inflation or
deflation on the economy outside of
extreme examples in whether these exist
as symptoms or causes of economic
activity. What is more broadly accepted,
however, is that it's the unexpected
inflation and deflation that tends to be
detrimental to economic activity uh
given that they tend to be more
disruptive to the equilibrium of the
market. And interestingly, there are
some economists who have advocated for
even higher inflation targeting.
Something highlighted by former Fed
chair Alan Blinder, who has highlighted
that some academics argue we should
increase the inflation rate with him
arguing that if we could go back in
time, a somewhat bigger inflation target
quote would have been a better choice.
However, one issue highlighted by the
economist and one reason we still have
2% inflation targeting despite the
arbitrary origin of it is that the fact
that this rate has already been set
makes it very difficult to now change.
Because a key component of inflation
targeting working is the credibility of
central banks. Something that changing a
long-term inflation rate could have a
negative impact on. So in a way, part of
the reason we have a 2% inflation target
from many of these developed nations is
inertia and the fact that now it's a
little difficult to change. Now that's
not to say inflation targeting methods
haven't changed over time. For example,
a paper by the Bank of International
Settlements found that while many
central banks for developed nations have
tightened their numerical inflation
targeting over time, uh moving from
targeting within a range to an explicit
figure, the time horizon for achieving
this objective and the focus on other
factors like employment has increased
over time. And there may come a day
where we see a meaningful shift in
inflation targeting. But as of today,
those are the arguments for why we have
2% inflation targeting. And it wasn't a
very empirical process to get to this
magical figure, but still some
meaningful arguments supporting and
justifying that targeting regime. But if
you like the math side of these
arguments and learning how statistics
can be used to better inform these types
of decisions or other scientific topics,
uh you should definitely check out
today's sponsor, Brilliant. Because as
much as I love talking my audience's ear
off about these different topics, it's
been demonstrated time and time again
that one of the most effective ways to
learn a given topic is through something
called active participation. I.e.
playing with the concept and working
through different exercises to enhance
your understanding of the subject, which
is something that Brilliant is
fundamentally built around. Brilliant is
a learning platform that hosts thousands
of interactive lessons on math, science,
programming, data analysis, and of
course, artificial intelligence. If you
want to impress your parents by
explaining how CHBT works to them or
just trying to understand like 80% of
market news these days, it's a really
cool and intuitive platform that helps
you become a better thinker and problem
solver. Uh their data module, for
example, has lessons covering everything
from data visualization to statistical
models and measurements that helps to
visualize and give examples of concepts
that can otherwise be fairly difficult
to get a grasp on. The lessons are also
bite-sized, making it easy to tackle a
subject over time, whether you have just
a few minutes a day or you just want to
lean in, hustle in, and put some hours
into one of the platforms many topics.
And the best part is that you can try
Brilliant completely free by heading to
brilliant.org/theplainbagel,
org/theplainbagel,
scanning the QR code on screen, or
clicking the link in the description,
which also give viewers 20% off an
annual premium subscription, which gives
you unlimited daily access to everything
on the Brilliant platform. So, thank
you, Brilliant, and thank you guys for
joining me today. I hope you found this
video helpful. If you did, please do
make sure to like, subscribe, all that
good stuff. It does help the channel
tremendously. And let me know your
thoughts on inflation targeting. Again,
it's going to be a contentious topic to
go over, but whether you think 2% makes
sense or you're someone who advocates
for deflation, happy to hear the
discussion down in the comments. Thanks
again for joining and as always be safe
out